<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://devingineer.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://devingineer.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-05-22T01:13:57+00:00</updated><id>https://devingineer.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">TryHackMe Active Directory Basics</title><link href="https://devingineer.github.io/blog/2024/tryhackme-active-directory-basics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TryHackMe Active Directory Basics"/><published>2024-08-17T05:10:20+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-17T05:10:20+00:00</updated><id>https://devingineer.github.io/blog/2024/tryhackme-active-directory-basics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://devingineer.github.io/blog/2024/tryhackme-active-directory-basics/"><![CDATA[<p>Lab Link: <a href="https://tryhackme.com/r/room/winadbasics">https://tryhackme.com/r/room/winadbasics</a></p> <p>This article goes into a walkthrough for the TryHackMe Active Directory Basics room of the Complete Beginner Learning Path.</p> <p><strong>Task 1: Introduction</strong></p> <p>In this task, we should launch the Windows server Virtual Machine by clicking on the “Start Machine” button. This will start up a browser-based machine to access the Windows server.</p> <p><strong><em>Answer: No answer required</em></strong></p> <p><strong>Task 2: Windows Domains</strong></p> <p>#2.1 In a Windows domain, credentials are stored in a centralised repository called…</p> <p><strong><em>Answer: Active Directory</em></strong></p> <p>#2.2 The server in charge of running the Active Directory services is called…</p> <p><strong><em>Answer: Domain Controller</em></strong></p> <p><strong>Task 3: Active Directory</strong></p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/819/0*LMwfvYzj9NWip7kV"/><figcaption>THM Domain Active Directory</figcaption></figure> <p>#3.1 Which group normally administrates all computers and resources in a domain?</p> <p><strong><em>Answer: Domain Admins</em></strong></p> <p>#3.2 What would be the name of the machine account associated with a machine named TOM-PC?</p> <p><strong><em>Answer: TOM-PC$</em></strong></p> <p>#3.3 Suppose our company creates a new department for Quality Assurance. What type of containers should we use to group all Quality Assurance users so that policies can be applied consistently to them?</p> <p><strong><em>Answer: Organizational Units</em></strong></p> <p><strong>Task 4: Managing Users in AD</strong></p> <p>In order to delete an organizational unit within Active Directory, we have to enable Advanced Features in the View menu and uncheck the option “Protect object from accidental deletion” in the OU properties settings. By default, OUs are protected against accidental deletion.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/396/0*xuxmZ-8pbq6heHoA"/><figcaption>Organizational Unit Advanced Features</figcaption></figure> <p>Delegation is the process of giving specific users control over certain OUs. We can delegate control over an OU by right-clicking the OU and selecting “Delegate Control”. For this example, we can delegate IT control on the Sales OU. This will open a window that will ask for users for our delegation and we can type in Phillip for the person we want to delegate control to.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/495/0*Uz57_P9VWiHZsD1O"/><figcaption>Delegation Control</figcaption></figure> <p>Once you click “Ok”, select the “Reset user passwords” option for the delegation task. Now Phillip should be able to reset passwords for any user within the Sales OU.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/492/0*fj9s8SmFSCER1xwd"/><figcaption>Delegation Control Tasks</figcaption></figure> <p>Now we can use Phillip’s credentials to log in via RDP to reset Sophie’s password.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/445/1*IuBS9U5HQkyn0Ppy3olzzw.png"/><figcaption>Phillip’s Credentials</figcaption></figure> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/319/0*UPAnTHEtXoebQ0uI"/><figcaption>Phillip Login via RDP</figcaption></figure> <p>Since Phillip does not have privileges to open Active Directory Users and Computers, we can use the Set-ADAccountPassword command in Powershell to reset Sophie’s password. Since we also do not want Sophie using the same password we set, we can force a password change at login.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/786/0*tHsj3afIt_2QkL-F"/><figcaption>Reset Sophie’s Account Password</figcaption></figure> <p>When we log in as Sophie via RDP with the new password, we are forced to change the password.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/349/0*7vnzS1FMjYJ-tk2u"/><figcaption>Sophie Login via RDP</figcaption></figure> <p>Once logged in, we can see there is a text file with the given flag we are looking for.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/287/0*xHWoc_exbDbFGk_C"/><figcaption>Flag on Sophie’s Desktop</figcaption></figure> <p>#4.1 What was the flag found on Sophie’s desktop?</p> <p><strong><em>Answer: THM{thanks_for_contacting_support}</em></strong></p> <p>#4.2 The process of granting privileges to a user over some OU or other AD Object is called…</p> <p><strong><em>Answer: delegation</em></strong></p> <p><strong>Task 5: Managing Computers in AD</strong></p> <p>By default, all machines within a domain are put in a container called “Computers”. We can see that there are some laptops and PCs corresponding to users on our network. We can create two new OUs, one for Workstations and one for Servers. We can move all the laptops and PCs to the Workstations OU and all the servers to the Servers OU.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/822/0*1K4-FAHlQ4DVXbJW"/><figcaption>Active Directory Workstations and Servers</figcaption></figure> <p>#5.1 After organising the available computers, how many ended up in the Workstations OU?</p> <p><strong><em>Answer: 7</em></strong></p> <p>#5.2 Is it recommendable to create separate OUs for Servers and Workstations? (yay/nay)</p> <p><strong><em>Answer: yay</em></strong></p> <p><strong>Task 6: Group Policies</strong></p> <p>Windows manages policies for different configurations through Group Policy Objects (GPO). GPOs are simply a collection of settings that can be applied to OUs. To configure GPOs, we can use the Group Policy Management tool.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/829/0*udBFQsDpGgxXB1iQ"/><figcaption>Group Policy Management Tool</figcaption></figure> <p>Within each OU, there are different GPOs applied to the users and computers within it. Note that a GPO will apply to the OU it is linked to and any sub-OUs within it. From the Default Domain Policy, we can go to Computer Configurations &gt; Policies &gt; Windows Settings &gt; Security Settings &gt; Account Policies &gt; Password Policy to change the minimum password length to 10 characters.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/775/0*n9XxvEAnCaL-t_SF"/><figcaption>Group Policy Management Tool — Password Length Policy Setting</figcaption></figure> <p>The first task we need to do is to restrict control panel access to users across all machines in our network except for the IT department. We will create a new GPO called “Restrict Control Panel Access” and look under “User Configurations” since we want this to affect all users. We can go to User Configuration &gt; Policies &gt; Administrative Tasks &gt; Control Panel and enable the “Prohibit access to Control Panel” setting.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/780/0*1txbXo2clnUu0EqK"/><figcaption>Restrict Control Panel Access GPO</figcaption></figure> <p>After creating our new GPO, we can assign the GPO to the Management, Marketing, and Sales OU to have it be applied to all the users in the domain except for IT.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/834/0*bfL1jIoQbifqjwa_"/><figcaption>Assign Restrict Control Panel Access GPO to OUs</figcaption></figure> <p>For the second task, we need to have the workstations and servers automatically lock their screens after 5 minutes of user inactivity. We could create a new GPO called “Auto Lock Screen” and apply it to the Workstations, Servers, and Domain Controllers OUs. As a simple alternative, we will apply the GPO to the root domain since they are child OUs of this domain and will be applied to all computers. Within the new GPO, we can go into Computer Configuration &gt; Policies &gt; Windows Settings &gt; Security Settings &gt; Local Policies to change the “Machine Inactivity Limit” to 300 seconds (5 minutes).</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/766/0*WM7XqNvoyLQQciKW"/><figcaption>Auto Lock Screen GPO</figcaption></figure> <p>After creating our new GPO, we can assign the GPO to the root domain to be applied to all machines within our network.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/829/0*UswgxsSqG4WEyWGx"/><figcaption>Assign Auto Lock Screen GPO to Root Domain</figcaption></figure> <p>Once the GPOs are applied to the correct OUs, we can log in as any user within the Management, Marketing, or Sales department. We will log in using Mark’s credentials via RDP. If we try opening the control panel we see a restriction message telling us we are denied by the administrator. If we also wait for 5 minutes, we will be logged out automatically.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/442/1*yyALweVqkquqfvnXQmgEIg.png"/><figcaption>Mark’s Credentials</figcaption></figure> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/552/0*qXB7dEEviq7bthsF"/><figcaption>Control Panel Operation Denied</figcaption></figure> <p>#6.1 What is the name of the network share used to distribute GPOs to domain machines?</p> <p><strong><em>Answer: SYSVOL</em></strong></p> <p>#6.2 Can a GPO be used to apply settings to users and computers? (yay/nay)</p> <p><strong><em>Answer: yay</em></strong></p> <p><strong>Task 7: Authentication Methods</strong></p> <p>#7.1 Will a current version of Windows use NetNTLM as the preferred authentication protocol by default? (yay/nay)</p> <p><strong><em>Answer: nay</em></strong></p> <p>#7.2 When referring to Kerberos, what type of ticket allows us to request further tickets known as TGS?</p> <p><strong><em>Answer: Ticket Granting Ticket</em></strong></p> <p>#7.3 When using NetNTLM, is a user’s password transmitted over the network at any point? (yay/nay)</p> <p><strong><em>Answer: nay</em></strong></p> <p><strong>Task 8: Trees, Forests and Trusts</strong></p> <p>#8.1 What is a group of Windows domains that share the same namespace called?</p> <p><strong><em>Answer: Tree</em></strong></p> <p>#8.2 What should be configured between two domains for a user in Domain A to access a resource in Domain B?</p> <p><strong><em>Answer: A Trust Relationship</em></strong></p> <p><strong>Task 9: Conclusion</strong></p> <p>Congratulations! You have completed the Active Directory Basics room.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/755/0*9vlO34UTWj4Bmj8v"/><figcaption>Room Completion Banner</figcaption></figure> <p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&amp;referrerSource=full_rss&amp;postId=b15c43b8871c" width="1" height="1" alt=""/></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">TryHackMe Windows Fundamentals 2</title><link href="https://devingineer.github.io/blog/2024/tryhackme-windows-fundamentals-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TryHackMe Windows Fundamentals 2"/><published>2024-08-17T01:24:54+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-17T01:24:54+00:00</updated><id>https://devingineer.github.io/blog/2024/tryhackme-windows-fundamentals-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://devingineer.github.io/blog/2024/tryhackme-windows-fundamentals-2/"><![CDATA[<p>Lab Link: <a href="https://tryhackme.com/r/room/windowsfundamentals2x0x">https://tryhackme.com/r/room/windowsfundamentals2x0x</a></p> <p>This article goes into a walkthrough for the TryHackMe Windows Fundamentals 2 room of the Complete Beginner Learning Path.</p> <p><strong>Task 1: Introduction</strong></p> <p>In this task, we should launch the Windows server Virtual Machine by clicking on the “Start Machine” button. This will start up a browser-based machine to access the Windows server.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/424/1*bWIWCfijlu7yvw4RWutEbg.png"/><figcaption>Windows Server</figcaption></figure> <p><strong><em>Answer: No answer required</em></strong></p> <p><strong>Task 2: System Configuration</strong></p> <p>#2.1 What is the name of the service that lists Systems Internals as the manufacturer?</p> <p>To answer this question, click on the “Services” tab of the System Configuration and look for “System Internals” in the Manufacturer section. The PsShutdown service lists Systems Internals as the manufacturer.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/566/0*heQmd-hVgQUXdtXv"/><figcaption>System Configuration — PsShutdown Service</figcaption></figure> <p><strong><em>Answer: PsShutdown</em></strong></p> <p>#2.2 Whom is the Windows license registered to?</p> <p>Within System Configuration, look for and run the command for the “About Windows” tool.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/567/0*-VHiWe2jiKTI0XD3"/><figcaption>System Configuration — About Windows Tool</figcaption></figure> <p>A popup with details about the current Windows Server and the license will appear.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/456/0*5XtOtUX26g-a9aje"/><figcaption>About Windows Tool</figcaption></figure> <p><strong><em>Answer: Windows User</em></strong></p> <p>#2.3 What is the command for Windows Troubleshooting?</p> <p>Within System Configuration, look for the “Windows Troubleshooting” tool. The full command path is located in the “Selected Command” box.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/566/0*y9U0P0uhpXKIdxgY"/><figcaption>System Configuration — Windows Troubleshooting Tool</figcaption></figure> <p><strong><em>Answer: C:\Windows\System32\control.exe /name Microsoft.Troubleshooting</em></strong></p> <p>#2.4 What command will open the Control Panel? (The answer is the name of .exe, not the full path)</p> <p>Within System Configuration, look for the “System Properties” tool. The command name to open the control panel is the last part of the full command path.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/566/0*q0H4xdgHBQAzqWvk"/><figcaption>System Configuration — System PropertiesTool</figcaption></figure> <p><strong><em>Answer: control.exe</em></strong></p> <p><strong>Task 3: Change UAC Settings</strong></p> <p>#3.1 What is the command to open User Account Control Settings? (The answer is the name of the .exe file, not the full path)</p> <p>To answer this question, look for the “Change UAC Settings” tool of the System Configuration. The command name to open the User Account Control Panel is the last part of the full command path.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/566/0*QSJfH2xdMrWLXqPU"/><figcaption>System Configuration — Change UAC Settings Tool</figcaption></figure> <p>This will open up the User Account Control Panel to change the settings for how programs make changes to the user settings.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/740/0*3O0c5KLnFg2OYFf0"/><figcaption>Change UAC Settings Tool</figcaption></figure> <p><strong><em>Answer: UserAccountControlSettings.exe</em></strong></p> <p><strong>Task 4: Computer Management</strong></p> <p>#4.1 What is the command to open Computer Management? (The answer is the name of the .msc file, not the full path)</p> <p>To answer this question, click on the “Tools” tab of the System Configuration and select “Computer Management”. The command for the tool is in the “Selected Command” window.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/569/0*PlDdPyiYBJE8gGx1"/><figcaption>System Configuration — Computer Management Tool</figcaption></figure> <p><strong><em>Answer: compmgmt.msc</em></strong></p> <p>#4.2 At what time every day is the GoogleUpdateTaskMachineUA task configured to run?</p> <p>Launch the “compmgmt.msc” command to open the Computer Management tool. Then go to Systems Tools &gt; Task Scheduler &gt; Task Scheduler Library, as shown in the following image. We notice that the GoogleUpdateTaskMachineUA task is scheduled to run every day at 6:15 AM.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/603/0*p2nicvajFMd1XP-F"/><figcaption>Computer Management Tool — Task Scheduler</figcaption></figure> <p><strong><em>Answer: 6:15 AM</em></strong></p> <p>#4.3 What is the name of the hidden folder that is shared?</p> <p>From the Computer Management tool within the System Tools, access Shared Folders &gt; Shares, as shown in the following image. Aside from the default Windows server shares, we notice there is one share named sh4r3dF0Ld3r.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/613/0*Ca-Bw3pMjHa02axc"/><figcaption>Computer Management Tool — Shared Folders</figcaption></figure> <p><strong><em>Answer: sh4r3dF0Ld3r</em></strong></p> <p><strong>Task 5: System Information</strong></p> <p>#5.1 What is the command to open System Information? (The answer is the name of the .exe file, not the full path)</p> <p>To answer this question, click on the “Tools” tab of the System Configuration and select “System Information”. The command for the tool is in the “Selected Command” window.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/566/1*mkWTfbDqcaCZ8u88Z-azAA.png"/><figcaption>System Configuration — System Information Tool</figcaption></figure> <p><strong><em>Answer: msinfo32.exe</em></strong></p> <p>#5.2 What is listed under System Name?</p> <p>Launch the “msinfo32.exe” command to open the System Information tool. Then go to System Summary, as shown in the following image. We notice that there is an item under “System Name” with the value “THM-WINFUN2”.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/690/0*RITnsdLUbRgKkPYR"/><figcaption>System Information Tool — System Summary</figcaption></figure> <p><strong><em>Answer: THM-WINFUN2</em></strong></p> <p>#5.3 Under Environment Variables, what is the value for ComSpec?</p> <p>From the System Information tool, go to the Environment Variables section, as shown in the following image. The path value is shown for the ComSpec variable.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/681/0*SPAt78pQ7BjA8AVd"/><figcaption>System Information Tool — Environment Variables</figcaption></figure> <p><strong><em>Answer: %SystemRoot%\system32\cmd.exe</em></strong></p> <p><strong>Task 6: Resource Monitor</strong></p> <p>#6.1 What is the command to open Resource Monitor? (The answer is the name of the .exe file, not the full path)</p> <p>Click on the “Tools” tab of the System Configuration and select “Resource Monitor”. The command for the tool is in the “Selected Command” window.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/563/0*iuNIU2gutnwjBiRo"/><figcaption>System Configuration — Resource Monitor Tool</figcaption></figure> <p>After launching the Resource Monitor, there are sections to view the current resources running on the CPU, Disk, Network, and Memory, along with a graphical view on the right.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/766/0*ozrmd0iuWnrbV5Ac"/><figcaption>Resource Monitor Tool</figcaption></figure> <p><strong><em>Answer: resmon.exe</em></strong></p> <p><strong>Task 7: Command Prompt</strong></p> <p>#7.1 In System Configuration, what is the full command for Internet Protocol Configuration?</p> <p>Click on the “Tools” tab of the System Configuration and select “Internet Protocol Configuration”. The command for the tool is in the “Selected Command” window.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/565/0*wCHm2OQKG6SQexyp"/><figcaption>System Configuration — Internet Protocol Configuration Tool</figcaption></figure> <p><strong><em>Answer: C:\Windows\System32\cmd.exe /k %windir%\system32\ipconfig.exe</em></strong></p> <p>#7.2 For the ipconfig command, how do you show detailed information?</p> <p>Launch or run the ipconfig command in the command prompt. We can check out the manual page for the ipconfig command and see all the example usages for the command.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/706/0*u6i-WNpgGvbIgAIf"/><figcaption>IPConfig Manual Page</figcaption></figure> <p>Using ipconfig with /all will show detailed information of the IP Configuration for the machine.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/652/0*zkiwYcQQbw5Os0Ax"/><figcaption>IPConfig Command /all</figcaption></figure> <p><strong><em>Answer: ipconfig /all</em></strong></p> <p><strong>Task 8: Registry Editor</strong></p> <p>#8.1 What is the command to open the Registry Editor? (The answer is the name of the .exe file, not the full path)</p> <p>Click on the “Tools” tab of the System Configuration and select “Registry Editor”. The command for the tool is in the “Selected Command” window.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/564/0*kl09qRIDF_5r1n2B"/><figcaption>System Configuration — Registry Editor Tool</figcaption></figure> <p>Launch the Registry Editor tool and we see a directory listing for users and devices on our machine. The Registry Editor is a central hierarchical database used to store information necessary to configure the system for one or more users, applications, and hardware devices.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/605/0*jDmvTitrrZhyZqj7"/><figcaption>Registry Editor Tool</figcaption></figure> <p><strong><em>Answer: regedt32.exe</em></strong></p> <p><strong>Task 9: Conclusion</strong></p> <p>Congratulations! You have completed the Windows Fundamentals 2 room.</p> <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/746/0*yjdvEslGtbeWQSLf"/><figcaption>Room Completion Banner</figcaption></figure> <p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&amp;referrerSource=full_rss&amp;postId=ff7fa4696529" width="1" height="1" alt=""/></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry></feed>